Vairo Di Pasquale

 $he/him \mid +39\; 3339271784 \mid vairo.dp@gmail.com \mid linkedin.com/in/vairo-di-pasquale \mid github.com/vairodp \mid vairodp.com/vairodp \mid vairodp \mid vairo$

AI/ML Engineer and Artificial Intelligence graduate having 6+ yrs development experience.

40% of my first name is already "AI", isn't it enough?

EXPERIENCE

Scalestack

Contractor

AI/ML Lead Software Engineer

August 2023 – Present

Remote

- Leading the AI Engineering team, focusing on the integration of cutting-edge AI/ML and LLMs technologies
- Architected and implemented an MLOps pipeline, streamlining the deployment and management of ML and NLP models into production environments.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams and stakeholders to define functional requirements, and led the effort in fine-tuning and training AI models to exceed performance benchmarks.
- Engineered, customized, and deployed a software co-pilot for sales reps, utilizing open and closed-source LLMs.
- Maintained and optimized production AI/ML models, implementing monitoring metrics to ensure consistent quality and performance according to company standards.
- Skills: Python, PyTorch, TensorFlow, LangChain, LlamaIndex, AWS, Docker

AI/ML Consultant/Developer

February 2023 – Present

EU/US

- Developed ML tools and led AI initiatives, streamlining adoption and deployment in enterprises.
 - Expert in computer vision and large language models, applying tailored solutions for digital transformation.
 - Technically proficient in PyTorch, Tensorflow, AWS, GCP, Docker, Kubernetes, and more.
 - Fostered effective collaborations between stakeholders and tech teams, enhancing project efficiency.
 - Key projects include AI tools, large language models, and computer vision solutions across industries.
 - Enabled AI/ML adoption, positively impacting enterprises of varying scales.

Machine Learning Software Engineer

January 2023 – August 2023

Polar Frequency

Remote

- Responsible for developing and maintaining Machine Learning, Deep Learning, and Natural Language Processing microservices in my AI team.
- Skills: Python, Transformers, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Huggingface, OpenAI, LangChain, Docker.

EDUCATION

Master's degree - Artificial Intelligence

Bologna, Italy

 $Alma\ Mater\ Studiorum$

October 2020 - Present

- Research in Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Natural Language Processing, and Computer Vision.
- Current **GPA: 4.0** (Italian Grading: 29/30). Awarded partial fee refund due to honors.

Exchange Student - Artificial Intelligence

Sundsvall, Sweden

Mid Sweden University

January 2022 - June 2022

- Main research topics: Natural Language Processing, Data Mining.
- Continuous exposure to ex-pats leading to the successful completion of a C2 English exam.

Bachelor's degree - Computer Science

Bologna, Italy

Alma Mater Studiorum

October 2020

- Coursework: Algorithms and Data Structures, Software Engineering, Operating Systems, Mobile App Development, Language Theory, Computability, and Complexity.
- The thesis result has supported the work that has culminated with a **peer-reviewed paper** presented at FACS 2021.

PUBLICATIONS

Corinne, a Tool for Choreography Automata

October 2021

FACS 2021: Formal Aspects of Component

Springer, Cham

- Developed a major extension of *Corinne*, a Python tool for reading, composing and projection of the Choreography Automata.
- Presented at a peer-reviewed conference hosted by FACS.

Stance Prediction | Python, PyTorch, Transformers

April 2022 – July 2022

- NLP project about Implicit Stance Prediction on Political Debates using Speech features.
- Different models to address the task, using BART, BERT, DistilBERT, wav2vec2 and MulT, the best of which reached an accuracy of 94,2% on the test set.

Fact Checking & POS Tagging | Python, Keras, Tensorflow, Scikit Learn November 2021 – December 2021

• NLP tasks about verifying the reliability of some statements by comparing with a given knowledge and the process of marking up words in a text with the correspondent grammatical tag.

AshtonTablutAgent | Java, Game Theory, MinMax, Tree Search

October 2021 – November 2021

• Java-based intelligent agent able to play Tablut using MinMax algorithm.

AstroNet | Python, Keras, Tensorflow, Scikit Learn

June 2021 – September 2021

- Deep Learning approaches for detection and classification of astronomical sources from radio images.
- Implementation from scratch of YOLOv4 and U-Net, with the latter reaching an accuracy of 97,3%.

Corinne-2 | Python

June 2020 – September 2020

- Extends and greatly improves "Corinne", a tool for modeling Choreography Automata.
- Presented as a Bachelor's Thesis and 1 year later presented as a published **peer-reviewed paper** at FACS 2021.

ToDaily | Java, Android, Android Studio

May 2020 - July 2020

• Android App for managing daily tasks.

CONTRIBUTIONS & EXTRACURRICULAR ACTIVITIES

Contributions in Open Source

May 2022 – Present

Active contributor for the LangChain's repo and for OpenAI's Gym, Minigrid, and Procgen.

AI Mentor for Ideathon & GDSC Europe collaborator

September 2022 – Present

Selected for mentoring in AI/ML for the Ideathon and GDSC Europe events.

Europe

Google Solution Challenge

March 2022 – June 2022

Presented Freebye, Android App for incentivize circular economy and waste reduction.

Core Member of a Google Developer Student Club

September 2021 – Present

Managing and organizing events in a GDSC with 200+ students.

Bologna, Italy

Online Summer School, Artificial Intelligence

June 2021 for 2 weeks

Main topics: Robotics, Computer Vision, AI for Medical Applications.

Nankai University, China

More Certifications

November 2021 – December 2021

"Advanced Deep Learning with Keras" & "Data Scientist with Python" on DataCamp.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Research field: Deep Learning, Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, Reinforcement Learning.

Libraries: SciPy (NumPy, Pandas, ...), SciKits (scikit-learn, scikit-image), Tensorflow, Keras, PyTorch, OpenAI Gym,

Matplotlib, OpenCV, Flutter, LangChain, LLamaIndex.

Technologies: Python, Linux, Windows, Git, Node, Jupyter.

Human Languages: English (C2), Italian (Native), Spanish (Current Learning).